Guide to the Alex Bittelman’s "Things I Have Learned" TAM 062
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Alex Bittelman’s "Things I Have Learned" [Autobiographical typescript]
1963
TAM 062
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
1.75 Linear feet (4 boxes)
Alex Bittelman was a Communist activist and theoretician who was one of the founders of the Jewish Communist movement in the United States. The collection consists of an autobiographical typescript.
Bittelman, Alex, 1890-1982.
Box 1-4
Provenance
Donated to the Tamiment Library by Ben Goldstein, 1974.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions. However, patrons must use the photocopied version only.
Historical/Biographical Note
Alex (Alexander) Bittelman (1890-1982), a Communist activist and theoretician who was one of the founders of the Jewish Communist movement in the United States was born in Berdichev, Ukraine. He became a printer, joined the Jewish Labor Bund, was imprisoned in Kherson (Ukraine) and elsewhere for his revolutionary activity, and emigrated to the United States in 1912, where he joined the Jewish Socialist Federation. In 1919, he joined the fledgling Communist Party (CP) and became the head of its Jewish Federation. During the 1920s. Bittelman served on the Party’s Politburo and was an ally of William Z. Foster in CP factional struggles. During the 1930s he wrote for the Daily Worker and the Communist, the Party’s theoretical organ. During the 1940s he oversaw Party work among Jews. During the 1950s he was one of several Party leaders convicted of violating the Smith Act and served time in federal prison. In 1959 was expelled from the CPUSA.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of an unpublished autobiography in 32 chapters describing childhood and radical activities in Russia; arrival in the United States in 1912; early Socialist connections; formation of the American Communist Party; factional feuds within the Communist movement; comments on its important personalities; including Earl Browder; William Z. Foster; Jay Lovestone; Charles E. Ruthenberg, and many others; travels to the Soviet Union; reflections on the New Deal and Cold War; thoughts on Bittelman's imprisonment for Communist activities; concern for Jewish survival; and general reflections.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged by chapter number.
The files are grouped into 1 series:
I. Autobiographical Manuscript, 1963.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Alex Bittelman Papers (Tamiment #62.1).
Bittelman, Alex, 1890-1982.; Browder, Earl-1891-1973.; Communist Party of the United States of America.; Foster, William Z., 1881-1961.; Lovestone, Jay.; Ruthenberg, Charles E. (Charles Emil), 1882-1927.; Autobiographies.; Communism--United States.; Jewish communists--United States.; Jews--Identity.; Political prisoners--Kherson (Ukraine); Right and left (Political science); Soviet Union--Description and travel.
- Series I: Autobiographical Manuscript, 1963.
  - Table of Contents, 0000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chapter 1. Hours of My Childhood (pp. 1-9), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chapter 2. My First Tragedy (pp. 19-30), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chapter 3. I Break Relations with the God of My Forefathers (pp. 31-45), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chapter 4. The World of Socialism and Revolution (pp. 46-79), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chapter 5. I Come to the Home of the French Revolution and the Paris Commune (pp. 80-100), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chapter 6. Back in Russia as the Revolutionary Tide Recedes (pp. 101-123), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chapter 7. Hunger Strike and Demonstration in Kherson Prison (pp. 124-163), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chapter 8. Exile in the Far North (pp. 164-129), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Chapter 9. My Last Months in Old Russia (pp. 220-236), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chapter 10. I Go to America (pp. 237-269), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Chapter 11. Becoming Americanized in the Midst of World War One (pp. 270-321), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Chapter 12. I Join in Founding the Communist Party of America (pp. 322-364), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Chapter 13. My First Visit to Soviet Russia (pp. 365-404), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Chapter 14. Collaboration with Foster: The Birth of the Foster-Bittelman Group (pp. 405-435), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Chapter 15. Leaders of the Communist International Favor Our Rivals: the Ruthenberg-Lovestone-Pepper Group (pp. 436-379), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Chapter 16. On the Approaches to the 1929 Economic Crash (pp. 480-531), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Chapter 17. New Lands, New Peoples, New Experiences (pp. 532-560), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Chapter 18. Years of the New Deal Epic (pp. 561-634), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Chapter 19. Trials and Executions (pp. 635-671), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Chapter 20. My Return to Jewish Life (pp. 672-712), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Chapter 21. Cold War and Cold Years (pp. 713-746), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Chapter 22. Six Steps to a Program for American Socialism (pp. 747-806), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Chapter 23. A Prisoner’s Reflections (pp. 806-890), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Chapter 24. A Prisoner’s Reflections, continued (pp. 891-920), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Chapter 25. The Ideal and the Real (pp. 921-944), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chapter 26. Looking to the Futures (pp. 945-1043), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Chapter 27. Jewish Survival and the Future of Mankine (pp. 1044-1118), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Chapter 28. In the World of Communist Thoughts (pp. 1119-1145), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Chapter 29. Reflections and Views of an Observer (pp. 1146-1241), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Chapter 30. China, Soviet Union, United States (pp. 1242-1285), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Chapter 31. Arabs and Israel (pp. 1286-1308), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Chapter 32. My Hopes and Wishes for America (pp. 1309-1367), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 10)